So infectious diseases, right?
إنها الأمراض المعدية
Infectious diseases are still the main cause
الأمراض المعدية لا تزال السبب الرئيسي
of human suffering and death around the world.
لمعاناة وموت البشر حول العالم
Every year, millions of people die of diseases such as T.B., malaria, HIV,
سنويا، يموت الملايين بأمراض مثل: السل والملاريا والأيدز
around the world and even in the United States.
حول العالم وحتى امريكا
Every year, thousands of Americans die of seasonal flu.
سنويا، يموت الآلاف من الأمريكيين من النزلات الموسمية
Now of course, humans, we are creative. Right?
لكن، البشر مبدعون أليس كذلك؟
We have come up with ways to protect ourselves against these diseases.
أتينا بطرق لحماية أنفسنا ضد هذه الأمراض
We have drugs and vaccines.
لدينا أدوية و أمصال
And we're conscious -- we learn from our experiences
ونستفيد من تجاربنا
and come up with creative solutions.
و نأتي بحلول إبداعية.
We used to think we're alone in this, but now we know we're not.
حسبنا أنفسنا الوحيدون في ذلك، لكننا ندرك الآن أننا لسنا كذلك.
We're not the only medical doctors.
لسنا وحدنا الأطباء.
Now we know that there's a lot of animals out there that can do it too.
هنالك العديد من الحيوانات التي تفعل ذلك.
Most famous, perhaps, chimpanzees.
أشهرها ، ربما الشمبانزي.
Not so much different from us,
ليسوا بمختلفين عنا كثيرا.
they can use plants to treat their intestinal parasites.
يستطيعون إستعمال النباتات لمعالجة الطفيليات التي تصيب أمعاءهم
But the last few decades have shown us that other animals can do it too:
لكن العقود الماضية كشفت لنا أن هذه الحيوانات تستطيع فعل ذلك أيضا.
elephants, porcupines, sheep, goats, you name it.
الأفيال، حيوانات النيص، الخراف النعاج، تستطيعون ذكرها
And even more interesting than that is that recent discoveries are telling us
وحتى أكثر حماسا من ذلك هي الاكتشافات الأخيرة التي تخبرنا
that insects and other little animals with smaller brains can use medication too.
أن الحشرات والحيوانات الصغيرة صاحبة المخ الصغير تستطيع إستعمال الدواء أيضا.
The problem with infectious diseases, as we all know,
كما نعرف، أن مشكلة الأمراض المعدية،
is that pathogens continue to evolve,
أن الكائنات الممرضة في تطور مستمر،
and a lot of the drugs that we have developed
والعديد من الأدوية التي قمنا بتطويرها
are losing their efficacy.
تفقد فعاليتها
And therefore, there is this great need to find new ways to discover drugs
ولذلك، هنالك حاجة ماسة لإيجاد وسائل جديدة لإكتشاف الأدوية
that we can use against our diseases.
بحيث تمكننا من مجابهة هذه الأمراض.
Now, I think that we should look at these animals,
الآن، انا أعتقد أنه بجب النظر إلى هذه الحيوانات،
and we can learn from them how to treat our own diseases.
وبإمكاننا التعلم منها كيفية معالجة أمراضنا نحن
As a biologist, I have been studying monarch butterflies for the last 10 years.
بصفتي عالم أحياء، كنت أدرس فراشات ملك الملكة في آخر عشر سنوات
Now, monarchs are extremely famous for their spectacular migrations
هذه الفراشات تشتهر بالهجرة المذهلة
from the U.S. and Canada down to Mexico every year,
من أمريكا وكندا إلى المكسيك من كل عام
where millions of them come together,
بحيث ان الملايين منها تكون سويا،
but it's not why I started studying them.
لكن هذا ليس السبب الذي جعلني أدرسها
I study monarchs because they get sick.
درست فراشات ملك الملكة لأنها تصاب بالمرض.
They get sick like you. They get sick like me.
تمرض مثلك أنت. تمرض مثلي أنا.
And I think what they do can tell us a lot about drugs
وإعتقادي أن ما تقوم به يمكن أن يخبرنا بالكثير عن الأدوية
that we can develop for humans.
التي يمكن أن نطورها للبشر
Now, the parasites that monarchs get infected with
الطفيليات التي تصيب فراشات ملك الملكة
are called ophryocystis elektroscirrha -- a mouthful.
تسمى إفريوسيستيس إلكتروسيرا ممتلئة الفم
What they do is they produce spores,
ما تفعله هو أنها تقوم بإنتاج الأبواغ
millions of spores on the outside of the butterfly
الملايين من الأبواغ على سطح الفراشة
that are shown as little specks in between the scales of the butterfly.
التي تظهر على شكل بقع بين قشور الفراشة
And this is really detrimental to the monarch.
حقا إنها ضارة لفراشة ملكة الملكة
It shortens their lifespan,
تقوم بتقصير عمرها،
it reduces their ability to fly,
وتقلل من قدرتها على الطيران،
it can even kill them before they're even adults.
وحتى أنها تقتلها قبل أن تكبر
Very detrimental parasite.
إنها طفيليات ضارة جدا
As part of my job, I spend a lot of time in the greenhouse growing plants,
كجزء من عملي، قضيت جزء كبير في النباتات الدفيئة
and the reason for this is that monarchs are extremely picky eaters.
والسبب في ذلك أن فراشات الملكة آكلات صعبة الإرضاء.
They only eat milkweed as larvae.
تأكل فقط الصقلاب كاليرقات
Luckily, there are several species of milkweed that they can use,
لحسن الحظ، هنالك العديد من الصقلاب يمكن أن تأكلها،
and all these milkweeds have cardenolides in them.
وجميع هذه الصقلاب تحتوي مادة الكاردينوليد.
These are chemicals that are toxic.
هذه عبارة عن مواد كيميائية سامة.
They're toxic to most animals, but not to monarchs.
وهي سامة لمعظم الحيوانات ماعدا فراشة الملكة.
In fact, monarchs can take up the chemicals,
في الواقع، فراشة الملكة تأخذ هذه الكيميائيات،
put it in their own bodies, and it makes them toxic
وتضعها في أجسامها و تحولها لمواد سامة
against their predators, such as birds.
ضد مفترساتها، مثل الطيور.
And what they do, then, is advertise this toxicity
وماتفعله لاحقا، هي أنها تعلن عن هذه السمية
through their beautiful warning colorations
عن طريق تلون جميل لكنه تحذيري
with this orange, black and white.
بهذه الألوان البرتقالية، السوداء والبيضاء.
So what I did during my job is grow plants in the greenhouse,
اذا، مافعلته أثناء عملي هو زراعة نباتات دفيئة،
different ones, different milkweeds.
عدة نباتات وصقلاب.
Some were toxic, including the tropical milkweed,
بعضها سام، يشمل الصقلاب الإستوائي،
with very high concentrations of these cardenolides.
بتركيز عالي جدا من مادة الكاردولين.
And some were not toxic.
والبعض لم يكن ساما.
And then I fed them to monarchs.
ثم قمت بإطعامه لفراشة الملكة.
Some of the monarchs were healthy. They had no disease.
بعض الفراشات كانت بصحة جيدة. لم تكن مريضة.
But some of the monarchs were sick,
لكن بعضها كان مريضا،
and what I found is that some of these milkweeds are medicinal,
وما وجدته أن بعض الصقلاب كانت له خواص إستشفائية،
meaning they reduce the disease symptoms in the monarch butterflies,
بمعنى أنها تقلل من أعراض المرض في فراشات الملكة،
meaning these monarchs can live longer when they are infected
هذا يعني ان هذه الفراشات تستطيع أن تعيش لفترة أطول وقت الإصابة
when feeding on these medicinal plants.
عن طريق تناول هذه النباتات الطبية.
And when I found this, I had this idea,
وعندما وجدت ذلك، أتتني هذه الفكرة،
and a lot of people said it was a crazy idea,
وعندها قال لي الكثير من الناس إنها فكرة مجنونة،
but I thought, what if monarchs can use this?
لكني فكرت، ماذا لو أنها تفعل ذلك حقا؟
What if they can use these plants as their own form of medicine?
ماذا لو أنهم يستعملون هذه النباتات كدواءهم الخاص؟
What if they can act as medical doctors?
ماذا لو أنهم يتصرفون كأطباء؟
So my team and I started doing experiments.
لذلك فريقي وأنا بدأنا بعمل تجربة.
In the first types of experiments,
في أول تجربة،
we had caterpillars, and gave them a choice:
كان لدينا اليسروع، وقمنا بإعطائه الخيار:
medicinal milkweed versus non-medicinal milkweed.
الصقلاب الطبي في مواجهة الصقلاب غير الطبي
And then we measured how much they ate of each species over their lifetime.
ومن ثم قمنا بقياس مقدار ما تأكله كل الأنواع في حياتهم.
And the result, as so often in science, was boring:
ونتيجة لذلك، كما في كثير من الأحيان في العلم، كانت مملة:
Fifty percent of their food was medicinal. Fifty percent was not.
وكانت خمسين في المئة من غذائها طبيا. و خمسين في المئة ليست كذلك.
These caterpillars didn't do anything for their own welfare.
هذه اليرقات لا تفعل أي شيء من أجل مصلحتها الخاصة.
So then we moved on to adult butterflies,
بعد ذلك انتقلنا إلى الفراشات الكبار،
and we started asking the question
وبدأنا طرح السؤال
whether it's the mothers that can medicate their offspring.
ما إذا كانت الأمهات يستطعن مداواة ذريتهم.
Can the mothers lay their eggs on medicinal milkweed
هل يمكن للأمهات أن يضعن بيضها على الصقلاب الطبية
that will make their future offspring less sick?
هل من شأنها أن تجعل لهم ذرية في المستقبل أقل مرضا؟
We have done these experiments now over several years,
قمنا بهذه التجارب على مدى عدة سنوات،
and always get the same results.
ودائما حصلنا على نفس النتائج.
What we do is we put a monarch in a big cage,
ما نقوم به هو وضع فراشة الملكة في قفص كبير
a medicinal plant on one side, a non-medicinal plant on the other side,
النباتات الطبية على جانب واحد، وغير الطبية على الجانب الآخر
and then we measure the number of eggs that the monarchs lay on each plant.
ثم نقيس عدد البيض الذي يتم وضعه على كل نبات على حدا.
And what we find when we do that is always the same.
وما نجده عندما نفعل ذلك هو نفسه دائما.
What we find is that the monarchs strongly prefer the medicinal milkweed.
ما نجده هو أن فراشات الملوك تفضل بشدة الصقلاب الطبية.
In other words, what these females are doing
وبعبارة أخرى، ما تقوم به هذه الإناث
is they're laying 68 percent of their eggs in the medicinal milkweed.
انهن يضعن 68 في المئة من بيضها في الصقلاب الطبية.
Intriguingly, what they do is they actually transmit the parasites
ما يثير الاهتمام، ما يفعلونه في الواقع أنهن ينقلن الطفيليات
when they're laying the eggs.
وعندما يضعن البيض.
They cannot prevent this.
لا يستطعن منع ذلك.
They can also not medicate themselves.
وبالمثل لا يستطعن مداواة أنفسهن.
But what these experiments tell us
لكن المهم أن هذه التجارب تخبرنا
is that these monarchs, these mothers, can lay their eggs on medicinal milkweed
غير أن هذه الفراشات، هؤلاء الأمهات، يمكن أن تضع بيضها على الصقلاب الطبية
that will make their future offspring less sick.
والتي من شأنها أن تجعل لهم ذرية في المستقبل أقل المرضى.
Now, this is a really important discovery, I think,
أعتقد أن هذا إكتشاف مهم للغاية،
not just because it tells us something cool about nature,
ليس فقط لأنها تخبرنا بشيء رائع عن الطبيعة،
but also because it may tell us something more about how we should find drugs.
ولكن أيضا لأنه قد يقول لنا شيئا عن المزيد حول كيف ينبغي لنا أن نجد الأدوية.
Now, these are animals that are very small
هذه الحيوانات صغيرة للغاية
and we tend to think of them as very simple.
و لازلنا ننظر إليهم على أنهم كذلك.
They have tiny little brains,
لديهم أمخاخ صغيرة.
yet they can do this very sophisticated medication.
ومع ذلك، تصنع هذا الدواء المتطور للغاية.
Now, we know that even today, most of our drugs
الآن، أصبحنا ندرك أن معظم أدويتنا
derive from natural products, including plants,
تشتق من المنتجات الطبيعية مثل النباتات،
and in indigenous cultures,
و في المواطن الأصلية،
traditional healers often look at animals to find new drugs.
يتابع المعالجون التقليديون الحيوانات لإيجاد أدوية جديدة.
In this way, elephants have told us how to treat stomach upset,
وبهذه الطريقة، الفيلة أخبرتنا عن كيفية علاج اضطراب في المعدة،
and porcupines have told people how to treat bloody diarrhea.
والشيهم علم الناس كيفية علاج الإسهال الدموي.
What I think is important, though, is to move beyond
ما أعتقد أنه مهم، رغم ذلك، هو أن نتجاوز
these large-brained mammals and give these guys more credit,
هذه الثدييات كبيرة الدماغ وإعطاء تلك الحشرات المزيد من التقدير،
these simple animals, these insects that we tend to think of
هذه الحيوانات البسيطة، هذه الحشرات، اننا نميل الى التفكير في
as very, very simple with tiny little brains.
كونها صغيرة وبأدمغة صغيرة للغاية.
The discovery that these animals can also use medication
اكتشاف أن هذه الحيوانات يمكنها أيضا استخدام الدواء
opens up completely new avenues,
يفتح آفاقا جديدة تماما،
and I think that maybe one day, we will be treating human diseases
وأعتقد أنه ربما في يوم ما، سنستطيع علاج الأمراض التي تصيب الإنسان
with drugs that were first discovered by butterflies,
بالأدوية التي اكتشفت أولا من قبل الفراشات،
and I think that is an amazing opportunity worth pursuing.
وأعتقد أن هذه هي فرصة رائعة تستحق المتابعة.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)